<specification 
              xmlns='http://berjon.com/ns/re-spec/' 
              xmlns:rs='http://berjon.com/ns/re-spec/' 
              version='1.0' 
              xml:lang='en'>

  <metadata>
    <title>Web URL Notifications</title>
    <styling type='W3C' status='ED'/>
    <date year='2010' month='09' day='21'/>
    <editors>
      <person>
        <name>John Gregg</name>
        <email>johnnyg@google.com</email>
        <company>Google</company>
        <company-url>http://www.google.com/</company-url>
      </person>
    </editors>
  </metadata>

  <section xml:id='abstract' type='w3c-abstract'>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <p>
      This document defines APIs for alerting the user outside of a web page
      by displaying notifications with Web content provided on a URL.
      For a broader overview of notifications, including definitions and use cases,
      see <a href="Overview.html">Notifications Overview</a>.
    </p>

    <p>
      This document extends and depends on Notifications specification providing
      text/icon notifications [NOTIFICATIONS].
    </p>
    <!--
    <ednote>
      <p>
        Last update: $Id: WebNotifications.xml,v 1.1 2010-10-13 07:42:38 jgregg Exp $.
      </p>
    </ednote>
    -->
  </section>

  <section xml:id='sotd' type='w3c-sotd'>
    <title>Status of this Document</title>
    <p>
      This document is an Editor's Draft and is not suitable for purposes other
      than reviewing the specification being developed.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='contents' type='toc'>
    <title>Table of Contents</title>

    <?respec-toc?>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='definitions'>
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <ul>
      <li><em>simple notification</em>: A notification which consists only of an icon and one or two lines of text.</li>
      <li><em>web notification</em>: A notification which consists of Web platform content, such as HTML or SVG.</li>
    </ul>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='introduction' normativity='not normative'>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <p>
      This specification extends the capabilities of Notifications defined in [NOTIFICATIONS] by allowing
      the notification to contain content supplied by a URL, such as HTML or SVG, allowing for interactive
      and dynamic notifications.
    </p>

    <section xml:id='permissions'>
      <title>Permissions</title>
      <p>
	Throughout this document, "notification permission is allowed" shall mean that 
	the permission level of the 'notifications' feature for the current
	security origin is <code>USER_ALLOWED</code>  or <code>DEFAULT_ALLOWED</code>
	in the meaning of [PERMISSIONS], and "notification permission is denied" shall mean 
	that the current permission level has some other value.
      </p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='html'>
    <title>Web notifications</title>
    <p>
      In addition to displaying simple notifications, some user agents may use a notification platform that is
      capable of displaying notifications which contain web content, such as HTML or SVG.  This supplemental 
      interface exposes that ability.
    </p>
    <schema>
      <title>supplemental NotificationCenter interface</title>
      <idl>
	<interface name='NotificationCenter' supplemental='true'>
	  <method name='createWebNotification'>
	    <returns type='Notification'>
	      <p>A notification object representing the new notification.</p>
	    </returns>
	    <param name='url' type='DOMString'>
	      The URL of a resource which contains content to be shown as the notification.
	      The URL parameter must be resolved relative to the base URL of the document or worker script.
	    </param>
	    <exception name='Exception'>
	      <p>
		If notification permissions are denied, this method will throw a <code>SECURITY_ERR</code>.
	      </p>

	      <p>
		If the URL is invalid or cannot be resolved, a <code>SYNTAX_ERR</code> is raised.
	      </p>
	    </exception>
	  </method>
	</interface>
      </idl>
    </schema>
    
    <section normativity='not normative'>
      <title>Unsupported content types</title>
      <p>
	User agents which use an existing notification platform and support only simple notifications may not
	support all types of web content.  These user agents may attempt to extract simple notification content
	from web content such as the <el>title</el> tag of HTML content as the notification.
      </p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='interactions'>
    <title>Interacting with notifications</title>
    <section>
      <title>Using window.opener</title>
      <p>
	A web notification is a separate window, and script running within
	that context should be able to communicate to other windows, subject to the
	rules which generally apply to cross-domain communication.
      </p>
      <p>
	Within a web notification, the <code>window.opener</code> property should be
	set to the window which created the notification.  If the notification was
	created by a worker script, <code>window.opener</code> should be <code>null</code>.
      </p>

      <p>
	The following example uses <code>window.opener</code> to return to the application
	which created the notification in response to a click, and then close the notification.
      </p>

      <example>
	notification.html
	---
	New email arrived! 
	&lt;a href="#" onclick="window.opener.focus(); window.close();"&gt;
	  Go to Inbox
	&lt;/a&gt;

	script.js
	---
	var notification = window.notifications.createWebNotification("notification.html");
	notification.show();
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id='algorithms'>
    <title>Queueing and displaying notifications</title>
    <p>
      These algorithm supersede the corresponding algorithms in [NOTIFICATIONS], providing for the
      fetching of the content URL.
    </p>
    
    <section xml:id='displaying'>
      <title>Displaying notifications</title>
      <p>
	When a user agent is to <em>display a notification</em>, the user agent should perform the following steps:
	<ol>
	  <li>
	    Fetch the resource given by <code>url</code> using the algorithm defined in [HTML5].
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    If the fetch algorithm returns error information, fire the <code>error</code> event on the notification
	    object and stop executing this algorithm.
	  </li>
	  <li>Fire the <code>display</code> event on the notification object.</li>
	  <li>Show the notification on the device, such as by calling the appropriate notification platform.</li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section xml:id='replacing'>
      <title>Replacing a notification</title>
      <p>
	When a user agent is to <em>replace a notification</em>, the user agent should perform the following steps.
	Let <em>old</em> be the notification to be replaced by <em>new</em>.
	<ol>
	  <li>
	    Fetch the <code>url</code> resource in <em>new</em> using the algorithm defined in [HTML5].
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    If the fetch algorithm returns error information, fire the <code>error</code> event on the <em>new</em> notification
	    object and stop executing this algorithm,m returning the error information.  The <em>old</em> notification is not affected.
	  </li>
	  <li>Fire the <code>close</code> event on the <em>old</em> notification object.</li>
	  <li>Fire the <code>display</code> event on the <em>new</em> notification object.</li>
	  <li>If the underlying notification platform supports replacement, replace <em>old</em> with <em>new</em> on the device.</li>
	  <li>If the underlying notification platform does not support replacment, remove <em>old</em> from the device and show <em>new</em> on the device.</li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>
    <bibliography>
      <bibentry xml:id='HTML5'>
	<title>HTML5: A vocabulary and associated APIs for HTML and XHTML</title>
	<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/</link>
      </bibentry>
      <bibentry xml:id='NOTIFICATIONS'>
	<title>Notifications</title>
	<link>Notifications.html</link>
      </bibentry>
      <bibentry xml:id='PERMISSIONS'>
	<title>Feature Permissions</title>
	<link>FeaturePermissions.html</link>
      </bibentry>
    </bibliography>
  </section>

</specification>

